<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assizes held in Warwick, August the first, 1681 by John Inett ...</title>
            <author>Inett, John, 1647-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9088</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12820524</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12820524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94204</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45868)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94204)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 385:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assizes held in Warwick, August the first, 1681 by John Inett ...</title>
                  <author>Inett, John, 1647-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Flesher for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXXIV, 34 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94204:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94204:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE ASSIZES HELD IN WARWICK. <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Firſt, 1681.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Inett</hi> M. A. late of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> College in <hi>Oxon.</hi> now Vicar of <hi>Nun-Eaton</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Fleſher</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94204:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94204:2"/>
            <head>TO John Chamberlain <abbr>Eſq</abbr> High Sheriff of the County of WARWICK. AND TO
<list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Charles Holt,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Knightlow,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Bridgman,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Charles Leigh,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Andrew Hackett,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Arthur Caley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And the reſt of the Gentlemen of the Grand Jury at the laſt Aſſizes.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAd not your Commands prevailed over my inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the enſuing Diſcourſe had never been more publick than from the Pulpit; but deeming it ill manners to diſpute the juſtice or expedience of your Commands, and Obedience better than Sacrifice, I reſigne to the Sentence you have paſſed; nor will I offer at an Apology for that which has your Commands to publiſh, to vouch your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, nor ſo much diſtruſt your goodneſs as to doubt of pardon for this Addreſs, to implore your Patronage and Protection of a diſcourſe of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> which by your Authority is made publick, and by your Example may be made uſeful; whom God has placed on high, on
<pb facs="tcp:94204:3"/>purpoſe to give meaſures to the Piety, and Loyalty of your Countrey; and from whom all inferiours muſt learn to diſtinguiſh Zeal from Faction, Religion from Grimace, and ſteady from pretended Loyalty: And that Countrey is happieſt where the vertue, and conſequently the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the intereſt of the Gentry are greateſt: But where Vice that great Leveller undermines their intereſt, and the Populace ſupplants them in their power, the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief is like the wounds of Conſcience, inſupportable, and with the wiſe man we may ſay, <hi>who can bear it?</hi> I have no more to add but my prayers to Almighty God, that from your Examples, your Countrey may learn to <hi>fear God and honour the King;</hi> that <hi>Your light may ſo ſhine</hi> before the common people, <hi>That they ſeeing your good works, may glorifie your Father which is in Heaven;</hi> that you may be Examples of Piety and Loyalty of ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ages; that you may Eternize the honour of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and your names be had in everlaſting remembrance: Which ſhall ever be the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gentlemen, Your moſt Obedient and moſt Humble Servant, <hi>John Inett.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94204:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Prov. XIV.</hi> part of the <hi>34. Verſe.</hi> Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>'TIS ſaid of the Ancient <hi>Romans,</hi> that they never began an action of any weight and moment till they firſt conſulted with their Gods; that they never ſate down to beſiege a City till they had firſt invited the tutelary Gods to forſake it: And fearing the prevalence of theſe their charmes, 'twas cuſtomary with the Nations againſt whom they fought, to offer a kind of violence to their Deities, chaining their Statues to ſecure their preſence and protection. The <hi>Roman</hi> thinking no valour enough to take a City not deſerted by the powers above: And the <hi>Barbarian</hi> no courage ſufficient to defend it when forſaken by them. Though theſe are deplorable Monuments of humane frailty, and ſhew us what wild extravagancies we ſhould run into, had we not a more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous light than that of Nature to be our Guide:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94204:4"/>Yet withal it demonſtrates a reverence and veneration to Religion imprinted by the hand of Nature; that the common notices of Reaſon taught the Gentile World, that the glory of a People; the ſucceſs of Armies, and grandeur of Nations depend upon it: and can our thoughts be leſs honourable, our ſentiments leſs generous of that Religion which exacts the moſt ſtrict and regular ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the moſt frank and univerſal charity; that commands our Brother ſhould ſtand as fair in our love as our neareſt intereſt; that derives its Being from the Eternal God, and by a ſeries of Miracles has been owned by the powers above? A Religion ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to the peace of Societies, the intereſt of Nations, and the common good of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that if Life and Immortality were not brought to light through the Goſpel, there is enough to recommend it to the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and care of Magiſtrates: which natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tends to heal the diſ-orders of State, to make Subjects peaceable and obedient, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſucceſsful, Princes Wiſe, Beloved and Glorious, and is that <hi>Righteouſneſs which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alts a Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is all this ſpeculation, or the fond Idea
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94204:4"/>of a cloyſtered genius, nor Melancholy para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox of a thinking brain, but the reſult of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, and a Maxime received in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks of the wiſeſt King: 'Tis a dictate from the Throne of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and a foundation for the moſt happy Government laid down by a Prince that had the Spirit of Wiſdome for his Guide; 'tis he affirmes, That <hi>Sin is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to a People, and Righteouſneſs exalts a Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtrength and weight of which aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be more clearly diſcerned if we firſt inquire into the ſeveral notions of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Righteouſneſs is ſometimes taken for that diſtributive juſtice, which conſiſts in the enacting and due execution of Laws, for a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to evil doers, and a praiſe and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe that doe well; and is ſo fixed to the authority of the Magiſtrate, that what is juſtice when it has the ſtamp of a power, may be a ſin when acted by a uncommiſſioned hand. Heaven has determined that he which imbrues his hands in anothers blood, ſhall atone for it with his own: But has not left it a common right of mankind to execute wrath upon thoſe that doe evil; but ſo annexed it to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94204:5"/>the authority which bears the ſword, that the death of the ſame Criminal that is juſtice by the Magiſtrate may be murther by a private Perſon. And 'tis happy for us that the King of Kings has put his ſword into no other but his Vicegerents hand; that Power is not the ſtandard of Equity; that the greedy mind is not the judge of Right and Wrong; that <hi>vengeance belongs unto the Lord,</hi> and by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or by his Subſtitutes, he alone repayes. And this Righteouſneſs is to the body Politick what the blood is to the body Natural, the publick health and vigor are preſerved by a due circulation of it; if it be too hot and run too high, the body is in a Fever; if Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick and cold and run too ſlow, 'tis a Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of languiſhing and conſumption; but then the body is ſound, when Righteouſneſs and Mercy go hand in hand, when they kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mix together, and truth looks down from Heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, But as Righteouſneſs is taken for that juſtice which reſpects the Magiſtrate, and is ſtyled diſtributive, ſo it is taken for the ſecond ſpecies of juſtice, which reſpects all men in their converſation and dealings one with another, and is by the Schools termed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94204:5"/>commutative. How much it is the duty of all men eſpecially of all Chriſtians <hi>to do juſtly:</hi> How far Trade and Commerce, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the ſtrength and glory of Nations do depend upon the juſtice of her Subjects; are things ſo obvious that I preſume it needleſs to inſiſt upon them, and ſhall paſs to the third notion of Righteouſneſs, and thus:</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Righteouſneſs is taken for that Piety that Heaven does juſtly challenge from us, and is but another word for Religion, and in the ſenſe of our Saviour, Chriſtianity is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but that Righteouſneſs which does exceed the Righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees. Now becauſe to be thus righteous is a duty incumbent on us all, and this noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Righteouſneſs comprehends both the other, I ſhall conſider it in this comprehenſive ſenſe, and in order unto that betake my ſelf to the clearing of this Propoſition which the words of my Text very naturally offer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Prop.</hi> That Religion tends to promote the intereſt and honour of Nations, and the peace and welfare of mankind.</p>
            <p>'Twould not become this place to attempt a ſurvey of the maxims of <hi>Mathaivell,</hi> to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at an eſſay to expoſe Cardinal <hi>Palivicini</hi>'s
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94204:6"/>carnal policy, or ſhew the impracticableneſs of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topias</hi> Laws, nor worth time to attack the foundation of Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his Book <hi>de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve;</hi> becauſe the greateſt votaries to Politicks, that ſacrifice Heaven to intereſt, and make Conſcience truckle to Reaſon of State, yet do not pretend to the Conduct of Nations without recommending a ſhew of Vertue, and at leaſt the Garb and Grimace of Religion. 'Tis enough therefore, if without attempting, to ſhew the weakneſs of theſe frames of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, it be made appear that Religion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes the intereſt and honour of all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by ſhewing, firſt, what it is that diſturbs the felicity and peace of mankind, and from what cauſes the ruine and ſubverſion of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are derived: And, ſecondly, the tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Religion to promote the welfare of mankind, the peace, the intereſt, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Nations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us inquire what it is that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts Government, and undermines the peace and welfare of States and Kingdoms. 'Twas Sin that invaded the joys of Paradiſe, and firſt introduced miſery into the world; 'twas that which once did curſe, which once did drown, and ſhall at laſt in flames conſume it.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94204:6"/>And 'tis her fruitful womb that diffuſes miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry throughout the Univerſe, nor need we look further to find the original of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicities which diſturb the tranquility and peace of mankind; but trace them home, and without the wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> we ſhall find the true Mother of the Child; their lines and features are ſo much alike, that the ſuffering very naturally carries us to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſin that brings it. Thus that the puniſhment might bear reſemblance with the ſin, the earth divides to puniſh the Schiſm of <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram;</hi> and they periſhed by fire, that with unhallowed hands ſnatched fire from the Altar. <hi>Sodomes</hi> unnatural flames bring new from Heaven to conſume it. The ſword puniſhed the cruelty of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin;</hi> and <hi>Achan</hi>'s Sin purſues him through all the Tribes, and at laſt ſeizes on the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. If <hi>David</hi>'s ambition carry him on to number the people, judgment ſtrikes direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at his darling ſin, and cures his pride by leſſening the number he prided in. Follow <hi>Iſrael</hi> down to <hi>Egypt,</hi> and their entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there carries us back to their inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in ſelling <hi>Joſeph</hi> thither. View them in <hi>Babylon</hi> under the yoak of their new Lords
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94204:7"/>the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> the place minds us of the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry they learnt from thence, and their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity points at their defection from their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sovereign: And ſo legible are our ſins in the miſeries that attend us here below, that he that runs may read. But to paſs by the conſequences of ſin ſo fatal unto Nations, becauſe it may be pretended that theſe are but the Accidental and not its Genuine and true born iſſue; let us inquire if Sin may not ruine a Nation, though the Divine juſtice ſtand neuter, and Judgment does not purſue it.</p>
            <p>And here though God ſhould withhold his hand, we ſhall find Nations may be ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſins thereof. Examine the miſchief of Injuſtice, behold the black train of Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, the Trophies of Diſcontent, the direful conſequences of Diviſion; and what a flood of miſery! what a deluge of ſorrow does at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them! View the ſacrifices to Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tell the number of Victims to that pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh ſin: How does that, like the <hi>Druids</hi> Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, gorge it ſelf with blood! And how many lives to every year fall Sacrifices to the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Princes! And how uneaſie is it to its native ſoyl, and to all the neighbouring King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94204:7"/>when it ſeizes upon a Throne! How ingrateful are the cryes of the Orphan and the Widow, there there is <hi>oppreſſion in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince!</hi> How meagre is the countenance, and how Ghaſtly the looks of the poor, when his face is ground by the injuſtice of the rich! See the conſequences of diſcontent, when moſt retired it makes at leaſt one man miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but how often does it invade the peace of Kingdoms, imbroyle Nations, and give Being to all the diſorders that may entitle Kingdoms wretched and unhappy! Such too are the iſſues of Diviſion, to which we owe the Tragick ſtories of inteſtine Wars. Let us compute the Maſſacres, ſumm up the Battles, and lay together the fatal Periods and Revolutions of Men and Kingdoms derived from no other cauſe, and 'twill be needleſs to draw together other Arguments to prove Sin the Author of humane miſery, <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of a People,</hi> the ruine of Kingdoms, and the bane of Nations. And if it be Sin which ruines, by the rule of contraries we are taught to conclude with <hi>Solomon,</hi> that <hi>Righteouſneſs exalts a Nation;</hi> which will yet be more clear from the ſecond thing to be inquired into, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94204:8"/>
            <p>Secondly, The tendency of Religion to promote the intereſt and honour of Nations and the peace and welfare of mankind. All Societies are made up of individuals, and each man is capable of a twofold happineſs, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal and Political; the one as man, the other as a member of a body Politick, and that is moſt properly accounted ſubſervient to the publick weale, which contributes to the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of mankind in this twofold eſtate. I ſhall therefore firſt inquire how.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Righteouſneſs tends to the common good of Nations, by contributing to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of each particular perſon, of which they are conſtituted and do conſiſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis eſſential to humane nature to contend for happineſs, that the higheſt degree of that we are capable of here below, is the reſult of Vertue and Piety, is ſo notorious that the confeſſions of its enemies is enough to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede all further arguments. Ask the man who feels the ſting of a guilty conſcience, that knows what it is to carry a Tormentor in his own boſom, to be always harraſſed with the frightful appendages of his own Vice; and hee'l ſoon reſolve us who's the happy man. Nay, take the jolly ſinner that not only bid<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94204:8"/>defiance to Almighty God, but to the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that attend upon other men, take him when his Pallate is cloyed, and his pleaſures palled, when he has compared a Surfeit and a Debauch together, and hee'l readily award for Temperance. But if he carry on the Frollick, and reſolutely for a time maintain a Paradox, but follow him to the place where he is to take his leave of the World, and ſo can have no temptation to belye his by-paſt minutes, there he retracts his erring Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and with his laſt breath proclaimes the good, the happy man; whoſe pleaſures are the joys of Temperance, and a holy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who hears not the Orphans cryes ſound his injuſtice in his ears, and feels not the ſmart of a wilful unrepented folly. And if the joys of good men were legible in their faces, and with the eyes of ſenſe we could but ſee the ſerenity, peace, and complacency which hovers over vertuous actions; or view the holy man ſurrounded by the ſoft and gentle whiſpers of the bleſſed Spirit, proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Jubilee to his Soul; or could the world be privy to the kind embraces of a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience preaching peace to the righteous, and gladneſs to the true of heart; the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94204:9"/>would retract, and it would be the common Contention, who ſhould be the moſt profitable ſervant to the Almighty, the moſt uſeful Votary to Religion, and ſtand the faireſt Candidate for Heaven. Beſides all this, thoſe ſatisfactions which are the objects of ſenſe, and ſtand high in the eulogies of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as well as good men, are the Children of Religion; to that we owe our ſecurity from Violence, Rapine and Oppreſſion; to that rejoycing under our own Vine, and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing undiſturbed under a Fig-tree of our own. <hi>Naboth</hi> enjoyes his Vineyard, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> his Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Prince maintains his Right, and the Subject is eaſie and undiſturbed in his Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Property, when Religion is the common Guardian; for our Secular intereſt, our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral peace, and all the bleſſings which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear this preſent life are but feuditaries to it. Wouldſt thou have thy honour unſtained, thy perſon ſafe, and thy right uninvaded, when Righteouſneſs rules the Sceptre there needs no Guard but Innocence. And what is thus rivited to the private intereſt of Prince and Subject, can have no other but an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious influence upon Kingdoms, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be of meaner uſe than to exalt a Nation:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94204:9"/>To which it tends a ſecond way, and that is,</p>
            <p>Secondly, By acquiring it an honourable eſteem among other Nations. He that will examine the unanimous ſenſe of Hiſtory, and the common ſentiments of men, ſhall ſtill find a due veneration to the powers Divine, and exact and regular juſtice ſet firſt in the Characters of an honourable and happy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. When theſe flouriſh, not a Poet but calls it the Golden Age; and all Hiſtorians how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever looſe themſelves, yet are loud in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of Juſtice, and are at pains in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals to perpetuate its Fame, and make the remembrance of it live for ever.</p>
            <p>This was the Baſis of the <hi>Roman</hi> greatneſs, and the reputation of their Generoſity, and Religion gained them more Conqueſts than their Valour and their Arms: whilſt their courage vanquiſhed Cities, their Religion car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried its Conqueſts to the very hearts, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercame the men. And that Prince is ever greateſt whoſe Dominion is in the hearts of his Subjects. But then did their Eagles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to droop, their ſucceſs to flagg, when <hi>Numa</hi>'s ſpirit of Religion was loſt, and their Ancient juſtice and integrity began to faile; 'twas the <hi>Punick</hi> Faith that fruſtrated their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94204:10"/>Valour, and their want of Religion that ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the progreſs of their Arms. When the juſtice and fidelity of a Nation are rightly blemiſhed, upon which all Leagues and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, all Trade and Commerce do depend, the credit is loſt, 'tis abandoned by all other Nations, left to confederate with its own vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and combate with the anger of Heaven, and the common contempt and ſcorn of men. For no Nation can be great in the reputation of others, where there is not juſtice and fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to recommend it to their Friendſhip and Alliance, and where theſe are wanting, All the world looks upon ſuch a Nation as God Almighty taught the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to do upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> as a Reed that may break or fail, may pierce or wound, but is unfit to ſupport the truſt of another Kingdom. But reputation and honour are the ſhadows of Righteouſneſs, and do as certainly and as naturally attend upon at as the ſhadow does upon the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or the rayes, thoſe Children of the Sun, upon the Father of lights. And let the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of Atheiſm produce a ſingle inſtance of any Nation that truly honoured God, that was not great in the eſtimation and love of men. Beſides giving it an honourable place
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94204:10"/>in the eſteem of Forreigners, there is a Third way that <hi>Righteouſneſs exalts a Nation;</hi> And this is,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By reccommending the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the love of all its Subjects, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it their intereſt to promote its peace and welfare. When the Religion of a Nation is ingaged for the ſecurity of every individual; and the publick juſtice makes the Tradeſman's ſhop as ſecure as if it were a Fort impregnable; when it eaſes the cares of the laborious Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, and is a Guard to the Farmers Folds, his Barns, his Flocks, his Herds, and Fields; and gives liberty to every Subject to rejoyce in the fruits of his own labour, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man has a ſhare in the proſperity and peace of the publick, and is bound by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to promote them; and his private being incorporated with the publick welfare, he muſt recede from his own advantage, and renounce his private intereſt before he acts the Traitor to the publick. I cannot ſay, that this ſhall make Fools or Madmen wiſe; that it ſhall heal the diſcontents, or eat out the proud fleſh of a Nation; that it ſhall make the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> good Subjects; that it ſhall work upon thoſe whoſe very mercies are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94204:11"/>cruel, whoſe Principles make them Traitors, and whoſe Religion is propagated by blood; that it ſhall ſweeten the nature of a diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented <hi>Achitophel,</hi> or reconcile thoſe to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that think well of none but which is managed by themſelves; that it ſhall take off <hi>Abſolom</hi> from making his Court to the rabble, and make him dutiful when the hopes of a Kingdom bids him diſobey: But with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and reaſon it may be affirmed that where the Divine juſtice is made a pattern for the humane; where laws are juſt and good, and theſe laws the rule of publick ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: each Subject ſtands bound by his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular intereſt to promote the peace and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and ſo far as in him lyes exalt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Nation. Beſides theſe, there is yet a fourth way, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, by preventing the judgments that ſin brings to ruine, and ingaging Providence to defeat the deſigns of ill men to undermine, a Nation. In the caſe of <hi>Eli</hi> God has taught us that <hi>He will honour thoſe that honour him, and thoſe that deſpiſe him ſhall be lightly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30.</p>
            <p>This is a common Rule to Providence in his dealings with mankind, and although in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94204:11"/>the judgments of God, many things are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable <hi>and paſt finding out;</hi> yet generally his revealed is a rule to his ſecret Will, and he ſcourges thoſe that by their ſins riſe in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt him, and is their Saviour and Deliverer that fight his battels againſt their ſins and follies; and no better reaſon can be aſſigned for the periods of Families, ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Nations, and thoſe mighty Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the World, which ſwell ſo many vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lums of Hiſtory. He that will conſider by what ways Empire and Dominion have cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled from one Kingdom to another, but look into the Origin of the <hi>Aſſyrian, Perſian, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> greatneſs, from what mean beginnings, and by what ſteps they grew up into the great Monarchies of the World: And again, how unaccountably they moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, ſunk under their own weight, and fell back again to their mean Originals; and how Proſperity and Grandeur wander from one Nation to another People, muſt needs be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by whom it is that Kingdoms Triumph and Nations proſper, who it is that <hi>pulls down one, and ſets up another;</hi> nor need we run fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the common obſervation of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, of the growth and decay of Nations;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94204:12"/>or that account of it which God himſelf has delivered to the World, to be reſolved that 'tis ſin makes the Rod to ſcourge the people, and Righteouſneſs is the moſt prevailing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive with the Almighty goodneſs to defend them; nor do the Scriptures render any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account of the Halcion days or various Scenes of miſery in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation. But to examine all the inſtances to this purpoſe, laid down in Holy Writ, or amaſs together the examples in profane ſtory, would require a Volume rather than a Sermon; and as the Apoſtle ſaith in another caſe, may be ſaid in this, <hi>Time would fail me to tell them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis enough that every happy Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is built on juſtice; that Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is Guardian to the eſtate and honour of the great, the Champion of the poor, and the Advocate of the Fatherleſs and Widow; that it cements and preſerves the bonds of peace and love; that it confines Prerogative and Privilege to their proper Chanels; that our Names, our Perſons and our Beds are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by it, and is the beſt ſecurity and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to Prince and People. Certainly then, that which cuts off thoſe Sins, which make the Almighty Proclaim War with a Nation;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94204:12"/>that which tends to the Tranquility and Peace of every Soul; that which indears the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to every Subject; that which makes the World court the Friendſhip and Alliance of a People; that which recommends a Nation to the protection and care of Providence; of ſuch a Righteouſneſs we may well ſay, that it ſerves the intereſt, exalts the honour of a Nation, and tends to promote the peace and welfare of mankind: Which is the aſſertion at firſt laid down, and being now proved, theſe Two practical Concluſions naturally follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Pract. Concluſ.</hi> That he is a enemy to his own peace and ſecurity, and the publick wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, that neglects the holy offices of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For if all ſhould purſue the examples of thoſe that are already Atheiſtical and Profane, and Religion periſh in the common Deluge of profaneneſs; this would put an end to the old diſtinction of, Mine and Thine; Right would be but an empty and inſignificant word; and the claimes of Allegiance and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty by Prince and People ſink to nothing. This would revive <hi>Lillburns</hi> name in a new race of Levellers; and it would certainly be one of the firſt effects of a general profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to parcel out their eſtates and level their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94204:13"/>perſons, with the common Crowd, that now by the greatneſs of their examples give countenance to the contempt of Religion, by which their perſons are ſecured, and their eſtates are guarded; and that reply once made to a Perſon of Honour, rallying at Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, That if there were no ſuch thing, it would be no ſin to ſtabb his Grace, as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had been ſtabbed by another hand, teaches us how much each mans ſecurity does depend upon Religion, how much 'tis each mans private, as well as the publick intereſt to promote it; and conſequently how much he's an enemy to his own peace and ſecurity, as well as the publick good, that is not a friend to Religion: And from hence ariſes a ſecond practical Concluſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> That they are the beſt Patriots that are moſt Solicitous to doe good; and by their practice and examples, encourage righteouſneſs in a Nation. This is the way to make a Kingdom flouriſh, to eſtabliſh it a renown great and laſting; to make it ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to its Subjects, admired by its friends, feared by its enemies, and proſperous under the conduct and care of Providence, and with the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> may we ſay <hi>happy are the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94204:13"/>people that are in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed are the people who have the Lord for their God.</hi> Now that we may be this happy people, and ours that Nation which Righteouſneſs does exalt, let us reflect upon the whole in order to our practice; and becauſe God and our Country command every one of us to doe our parts in our ſeveral ſtations, I ſhall conclude with a particular Application of this general diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>'Tis not the buſineſs I am call'd hither for to read Lectures of Juſtice to you (my Lords) whoſe great experience, wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in our Laws, make you perfectly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the true and proper meaſures of it. But there needs no Apology to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates, for the Goſpel meek and humble Method of Addreſs, if as an Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour of Chriſt I preſume to beſeech <hi>Your Lordſhips</hi> to maintain the glory of that God, by whom the higher powers are ordained; the dignity of that Sacred Perſon you repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and the honour of the places which you fill; to perſevere in that integrity which has made the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bench ſo glorious, and in your wiſe diſtribution of juſtice to fill up all the meaſures of men, <hi>That fear God, hate Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94204:14"/>and honour the King.</hi> May you imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate that God you adore, in pleading the cauſe of the Fatherleſs and the Widow, and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe whoſe innocence and neceſſities re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them to your care; may your <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice run down in ſuch mighty ſtreams,</hi> as may at once bear down the reigning ſins of the Nation, and the malice of your enemies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; may your Righteouſneſs make the Scarlet too great for envy, and ſtop the mouths of thoſe that blaſpheme God and the King, and watch for your halting; may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sentence from your mouths, every ſtroke from your hands, ſo intirely quadrate with our Laws, which are juſt and good, that diſcontent may it ſelf not blaſt your actions, nor dare to call them by the hated name of Arbitrary: May your Righteouſneſs be a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror unto Vice, an incouragement to Vertue; may it bring glory to God, reputation to your ſelves, and exalt the honour of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But now leſt any think juſtice the duty of Magiſtrates alone, and no Righteouſneſs but that of Governours requiſite to exalt a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I muſt inlarge to ſhew the duties our Religion, and our Countrey challenge from
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94204:14"/>every true <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, and every Orthodox Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>Who is not ſenſible of that cloud which hangs over our heads, and is ready to diſſolve in ſhowres of vengeance? How the Conclave contrives, and what active emiſſaries it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys to ruine and undo us? How our home bred quarrels lay us open to their malice, and prepare a way to the <hi>Romans</hi> to take our place and our Nation from us; and how much danger we are in, of their entrance at that gap which we have opened by our own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions: This is that we are all ſenſible of, and the cry of the Kingdom is that of the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the ſtorm, <hi>we periſh, we periſh;</hi> and yet whilſt with them we own, nothing but the Lord can ſave us, whoſe Piety ſtands in the Gap, whoſe Repentance invites the Salvation of our God? But on the contrary, whilſt we behold Church and State ready to be ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, how generally do we forget that iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is the ruine of a people, and make no other uſe of our danger, but maliciouſly to reflect on the conduct of our Governours? Thus, <hi>Iſaac</hi> like, we carry the fewel though marked out our ſelves to be the ſacrifice, and by a conjunction of ſin and folly, prepare a Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94204:15"/>pile for our ſelves, the beſt Religion, and the moſt excellent frame of Government.</p>
            <p>We, like <hi>David,</hi> are in a ſtrait, ſeem to have nothing but choice of Plagues laid before us; either to give up our Necks to the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoak, which our Fathers were not able to bear; or elſe let the Kirk bore our ears to mark us for her ſlaves, and with a ſolemn League faſten us to the ſtool of Repentance: and our ſins have brought us to ſuch a paſs, that there ſeems a fatal neceſſity of the one, or other, or elſe to be ground betwixt them both. <hi>Though all this be come upon us,</hi> we may add with the Prophet, <hi>who lays it to heart!</hi> Good God! what ſhall we then doe, or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we fly! will thy goodneſs deliver, which we have ſo much abuſed! or thy hand ſave, that is juſtly ſtretched forth to puniſh us! is not vengeance thine, and wilt not thou repay! can our ſins, that are before thy Throne to cry for vengeance, come down unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! or our horrid impieties eſcape thy hand! wilt not thou viſit us for our ſins, <hi>and will not thy Soul be avenged upon ſuch a people as this:</hi> That uſe thy forbearance, thy mercies and deliverances, to encourage and heighten our ſins, and perpetuate our Rebellion againſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94204:15"/>thee; that deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeak evil of dignities; that uſe the clemency of a Prince to libel and reproach him, and fly in the face of Government; plenty to fat themſelves for the day of ſlaughter; and peace but to gain time to prepare for war, and make the ſword ſharper for the day of battel. Is this the way to make a Kingdom flouriſh, to invite For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners to ſay we are <hi>a wiſe and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people,</hi> or buoy up the ſinking Credit of our Countrey? Is this the way to invite the Papiſt to forſake his errours, to bring him to the embraces of the Proteſtant faith, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs there is no Religion that <hi>has Statutes and Judgments ſo righteous</hi> as ours? And is this the Righteouſneſs that will exalt our Nation? No! 'tis theſe impieties that are a reproach to the name of Proteſtant! 'tis theſe provoke the <hi>Gallick</hi> cruelty to attempt to root out that Name from under Heaven; and affronts we daily ſee put upon our Government, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly help to kindle the rage of <hi>France</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Brethren there. 'Tis theſe are a ſhame to the truth we own, a diſhonour to our God and our Countrey, and unleſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, will certainly be the ruine of our Souls, our Religion and our Nation.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:94204:16"/>
            <p>What made <hi>Iſrael</hi> captive in <hi>Babylon,</hi> what gave them up to the Conqueſt of <hi>Pompey,</hi> and to a final deciſion by the hand of <hi>Titus?</hi> what brought that miſerable bondage the poor Chriſtians of the Eaſt labour under, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thoſe once flouriſhing Churches to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> power? If it were their ſins, we have as ſtrong grounds to believe it juſt with God to take away his Goſpel from us, to permit Superſtition to invade, and Idolatry once more to overrun us; and as often as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template how fatal ſins have been to other people, and with an impartial eye look upon our own, we muſt with our Saviour cry out, that <hi>except we repent, we ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt therefore beſeech you, Brethren, by all that's Sacred, by all that's dear to wiſe and good men, for your Souls, your Religion, and your Countries ſake, that <hi>your light may ſhine before men,</hi> that with good works, and holy lives you may adorn the Proteſtant faith and name, that you forſake your ſins, and turn unto the Lord your God; 'tis this muſt ſtop the wrath which is gone out againſt us, ſtay the hand of the deſtroying Angel, and prevail with God, that neither our Religion, our King, nor our ſelves may periſh. Let us
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94204:16"/>fore ſet our ſelves to live up to that Religion which God has planted, and by a ſeries of miracles has preſerved amongſt us. Let us confute the Papiſt by living better lives, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that we have a better Religion, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better Chriſtians, and better Subjects. Let us <hi>put on the Armour of God, and not only name the Name of Chriſt, but depart from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> Thus God will fight againſt thoſe that fight againſt us, and our Religion will ſtand impregnable notwithſtanding all the deſigns of men. Let me therefore beſeech you, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, in this day of tryal, when ruine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, and judgment threatens; not to think (as the practice of too many is) to excuſe your neglect of Piety and Repentance by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting all our dangers to the ill conduct of our Governours; do not think your love or zeal to your Religion, or your Country con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in reviling of authority, or ſpeaking evil of the Rulers of the people; but let us look at home, correct the ſins that lodge within our own walls, ſtrive whoſe life ſhall be the greateſt ornament to our Religion, who ſhall be firſt in the way to Heaven, and who fitteſt for the Crown of Glory and Immortality, and the ineffable felicities of the Saints in light;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94204:17"/>thus at once you'l ſerve your god, your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, your Countrey, and your ſelves, and by the ſame methods promote the honour of the former, and the intereſt and felicity of the latter. Thus Heaven and Earth, your Preſent and your Eternal intereſt unite, to command your utmoſt induſtry, to make Righteouſneſs beloved, and practis'd, Vertue ſacred, and Religion obeyed and honoured. Thus ſhall we be the people in the happy caſe, <hi>who have the Lord for our God.</hi> Thus may we be happy here, and bleſſed hereafter. Thus that Righteouſneſs which makes this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and our Religion flouriſh, will make us <hi>ſhine at laſt like Stars in Glory,</hi> and that which exalts our Nation, will exalt us all at laſt to Heaven.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
